<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.4.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://yazin.co/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://yazin.co/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-08-24T14:31:17+03:00</updated><id>https://yazin.co/</id><title type="html">Yazin builds a SaaS business</title><subtitle>My name's Yazin, and I'm a Product Manager building a Software as a Service (SaaS) business from the ground up.
</subtitle><author><name>Yazin Alirhayim</name><email>hi@yaz.in</email></author><entry><title type="html">From 0 to ICO, in 10 days</title><link href="https://yazin.co/vc-ico-idea/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From 0 to ICO, in 10 days" /><published>2017-08-23T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2017-08-23T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>https://yazin.co/vc-ico-idea</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yazin.co/vc-ico-idea/">&lt;p&gt;So after some conversations with a few friends, and due to the apparent explosion of interest in ICOs in the past few months, I decided to give ICOs a shot. There was no long-term plan here — I simply wanted to move quickly and run a test to see if it’s actually possible to raise a bunch of money for a project. The project itself didn’t matter so much — to quote Miley Cyrus: “it’s the climb”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew I’d be sharing the experience later on, so I used &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.notion.so/invite/link/dc8dc67d56334ea984e7757d90adb311&quot;&gt;Notion&lt;/a&gt; for planning and documenting everything. It works great — mostly like a Google Doc with nested pages. Here’s what that looked like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/notion-blockchain.png&quot; alt=&quot;Notion - Blockchain ICO plan&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ported everything over here, so you can just read along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-plan&quot;&gt;The Plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understand the Basics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find an Idea&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[15 July] Pre-announce the ICO&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[16 July] Draft the White Paper&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[17 July] Draft copy for the Website&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[19 July] Launch the website&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[20 July] Recruit prominent advisors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[21 July] Create a basic Smart Contract&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[22 July] Reach out to ICO lists&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[23 July] Publicity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[25 July] Launch ICO&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I figured if I could get everything done in about 10 days, it’d be great — even if the ICO doesn’t end up raising anything. It’s an experiment after all… and the worst case scenario means I learn a ton about Ethereum and ICOs in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-basics-&quot;&gt;The Basics 🍼&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the start, I knew very little about cryptocurrencies and blockchain so some reading was in order. After a lot of wasted time reading vague, regurgitated garbage, I eventually found a few resources that provided the most bang for word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@nik5ter/explain-bitcoin-like-im-five-73b4257ac833&quot;&gt;Explain Bitcoin like I’m 5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_160oMzblY8&quot;&gt;Blockchain 101: A visual demo — Video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://solidity.readthedocs.io/en/latest/introduction-to-smart-contracts.html&quot;&gt;Ethereum WhitePaper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the basics covered, we can proceed to learn more on Ethereum. Go through the last few links before reading along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ethereum-concepts&quot;&gt;Ethereum Concepts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ethereum/wiki/wiki/White-Paper&quot;&gt;https://github.com/ethereum/wiki/wiki/White-Paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;section-optional&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You can &lt;a href=&quot;#skip-ethereum-technical&quot;&gt;skip this section ⏬&lt;/a&gt; if you’re not technical&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;A few of these concepts are crucial to grasp if you’re looking to understand how Ethereum &lt;em&gt;differs&lt;/em&gt; from Bitcoin.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;For me, these were:&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;h4 id=&quot;accounts&quot;&gt;Accounts&lt;/h4&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;An Ethereum account contains four fields:&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;nonce&lt;/strong&gt; , a counter used to make sure each transaction can only be processed once&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The account’s current &lt;strong&gt;ether balance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The account’s &lt;strong&gt;contract code&lt;/strong&gt; , if present&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The account’s &lt;strong&gt;storage&lt;/strong&gt; (empty by default)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;In general, there are two types of accounts: &lt;strong&gt;externally owned accounts&lt;/strong&gt; , controlled by private keys, and &lt;strong&gt;contract accounts&lt;/strong&gt; , controlled by their contract code.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;An externally owned account has no code&lt;/em&gt; , and one can send messages from an externally owned account by creating and signing a transaction. In a contract account, &lt;em&gt;every time the contract account receives a message its code activates&lt;/em&gt; , allowing it to read and write to internal storage and send other messages or create contracts in turn.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;h4 id=&quot;contracts&quot;&gt;Contracts&lt;/h4&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Note that “contracts” in Ethereum should not be seen as something that should be “fulfilled” or “complied with”; rather, they are more like “autonomous agents” that live inside of the Ethereum execution environment, &lt;strong&gt;always executing a specific piece of code when “poked” by a message or transaction&lt;/strong&gt; , and having direct control over their own ether balance and their own key/value store to keep track of persistent variables.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;h4 id=&quot;transactions&quot;&gt;Transactions&lt;/h4&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The term “transaction” is used in Ethereum to refer to the signed data package that stores a message to be sent from an externally owned account. Transactions contain:&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;the recipient of the message;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;a signature identifying the sender;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;the amount of ether to transfer from the sender to the recipient;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;an optional data field;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;STARTGAS&lt;/code&gt; value, representing the maximum number of computational steps the transaction execution is allowed to take; and&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;GASPRICE&lt;/code&gt; value, representing the fee the sender pays per computational step.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;h4 id=&quot;messages&quot;&gt;Messages&lt;/h4&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Contracts have the ability to send “messages” to other contracts. Messages are virtual objects that are never serialized and exist only in the Ethereum execution environment. A message contains:&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;the sender of the message (implicit);&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;the recipient of the message;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;the amount of ether to transfer alongside the message;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;an optional data field; and&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;STARTGAS&lt;/code&gt; value.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Essentially, &lt;strong&gt;a message is like a transaction&lt;/strong&gt; , &lt;em&gt;except it is produced by a contract and not an external actor&lt;/em&gt; . A message is produced when a contract currently executing code executes the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CALL&lt;/code&gt; opcode, which produces and executes a message. Like a transaction, a message leads to the recipient account running its code.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;h3 id=&quot;ethereum-code-execution&quot;&gt;Ethereum Code Execution&lt;/h3&gt;

  &lt;h4 id=&quot;storage&quot;&gt;Storage&lt;/h4&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The operations have access to three types of space in which to store data:&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The stack, a last-in-first-out container to which values can be pushed and popped&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Memory, an infinitely expandable byte array&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The contract’s long-term storage, a key/value store. Unlike stack and memory, which reset after computation ends, storage persists for the long term.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The code can also access the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;value&lt;/code&gt; , &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sender&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;data&lt;/code&gt; of the incoming message, as well as block &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;header&lt;/code&gt; data, and the code can also return a byte array of data as an output.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;h4 id=&quot;blockchain--mining&quot;&gt;Blockchain &amp;amp; Mining&lt;/h4&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The main difference between Ethereum and Bitcoin with regard to the blockchain architecture is that, unlike Bitcoin, &lt;strong&gt;Ethereum blocks contain a copy of both the transaction list and the most recent state&lt;/strong&gt; . Aside from that, two other values, the block number and the difficulty, are also stored in the block.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;h3 id=&quot;questions-i-had-that-were-later-clarified&quot;&gt;Questions I had that were later clarified:&lt;/h3&gt;

  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;If gas is used every time the program is executed, and the program is executed on multiple nodes (presumably, simultaneously) — what’s to prevent all of the gas from getting consumed &lt;em&gt;each time&lt;/em&gt; ? Answer &lt;a href=&quot;https://ethereum.stackexchange.com/a/21091/14187&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Where is stuff actually &lt;em&gt;stored&lt;/em&gt; ? Answer &lt;a href=&quot;https://ethereum.stackexchange.com/a/6413/14187&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;skip-ethereum-technical&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;finding-an-idea-&quot;&gt;Finding an Idea 🤔&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armed with a better understanding of the blockchain, Bitcoin and more importantly &lt;em&gt;Ethereum&lt;/em&gt; … we’ll need an idea to execute on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.gdax.com/how-to-raise-money-on-a-blockchain-with-a-token-510562c9cdfa&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;, we should find an idea that can benefit from Network Effects (i.e. the more users that use it, the better it gets).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;examples-of-successful-icos&quot;&gt;Examples of successful ICOs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://storj.io/&quot;&gt;Storj.io&lt;/a&gt; : Storj is a system for decentralized file storage. Like Bitcoin or Ethereum, there is no central operator of the network. The project raised $30m through a crowdfund of their token, Storjcoin, on the blockchain.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://steemit.com/&quot;&gt;Steem&lt;/a&gt; : a decentralized Reddit where people are paid to contribute news and content.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You’ll notice one other thing about these “projects” or “apps”: they are really decentralized software protocols. A protocol is a fancy technical term that means: a standard language that lets a bunch of people on the internet work together on a specific problem. — &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.coinbase.com/app-coins-and-the-dawn-of-the-decentralized-business-model-8b8c951e734f&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;found-an-idea&quot;&gt;Found an Idea&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simple. Build a VC firm, based on the blockchain. Not complicated technically, but also solves an apparently existing problem (only available to ultra-high net worth individuals and institutions). Admittedly, I didn’t think too much about this — I just wanted to get the experiment started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could’ve gone with something more exotic (and that actually benefits from the distributed nature of the blockchain), but it’s unlikely I would’be been able to make much progress in just 10 days on anything more than the simplest concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the name, I had a number of choices of available domain names:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://herd.capital&quot;&gt;herd.capital&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://collect.capital&quot;&gt;collect.capital&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://general.capital&quot;&gt;general.capital&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://general.fund&quot;&gt;general.fund&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://every.fund&quot;&gt;every.fund&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://verify.fund&quot;&gt;verify.fund&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://unit.fund&quot;&gt;unit.fund&lt;/a&gt; ← ended up using this&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lot.fund&quot;&gt;lot.fund&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://elect.fund&quot;&gt;elect.fund&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://elected.fund&quot;&gt;elected.fund&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-1-pre-announcement-of-the-ico-&quot;&gt;Day 1: Pre-announcement of the ICO 🔔&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pre-announcement is the announcement of the future project in the communities of cryptocurrency investors, such as Bitcoin Talk, Reddit and others. You write up an executive summary - a small presentation to investors, in which you explain the essence and purpose of the ICO project. After the executive summary, you get the first feedback, which you can use to gauge investor interest in the project, and questions to fill up your website FAQ section with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You can pre-announce here:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;https://bitcointalk.org/index.php?board=159.0&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;https://www.reddit.com/r/icocrypto/&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;https://www.reddit.com/r/Bitcoin/&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would make sense to use some sort of PR group specializing in crypto, like: &lt;a href=&quot;https://vindynegroup.com/&quot;&gt;https://vindynegroup.com/&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://blockbounty.io/launch-bounty-campaign&quot;&gt;Blockbounty&lt;/a&gt;. I didn’t have time for all that, so I just winged it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Things to include in the pre-announcement:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Summary of the offering
 &lt;a href=&quot;http://unit.Fund&quot;&gt;Unit.Fund&lt;/a&gt; is an Ethereum based closed-ended fund that allows anyone to invest in the world’s best startups. No minimum investment amounts, and no minimum annual income means that anyone can now invest in the VC fund of the future — and realize the kind of gains only the rich could get access to.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Social media links:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/unit_fund&quot;&gt;https://twitter.com/unit_fund&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://join.slack.com/t/unitfund/shared_invite/MjEzMzk0NDQwODIwLTE1MDAxMjAzOTQtZWQ2MWYwMmIxYQ&quot;&gt;Slack Invite link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Posted:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I posted the following pre-announcements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bitcointalk.org/index.php?topic=2023143&quot;&gt;BitcoinTalk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/icocrypto/comments/6nrgio/preico_unit_fund_the_internets_own_vc_firm/&quot;&gt;Reddit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reddit fared alot better than BitcoinTalk. The overwhelming feedback from BitcoinTalk was to post with an account that’s got more than just “Newbie” status (they didn’t put it quite as nicely though).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-2-draft-the-white-paper-&quot;&gt;Day 2: Draft the White Paper 📝&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ah yes, time to polish up those writing skillz. I decided to start with an outline, which I’ll use to organize my thoughts. I’d then expand on that, add some fancy technical terms and references, and then make it look official.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bullet-points&quot;&gt;Bullet Points&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We’re the “Y Combinator” of online startups&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Today you’re putting money in ICOs and don’t know what you are getting. We solve that problem by pooling the money and vetting our investments ourselves with strict criteria. Oh, and we also have the best VCs as advisors to help guide us.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Flipping the investor model on it’s head. Instead of having a small group of Limited Partners invest all the money (and receive the lion’s share of the return), we’re going to raise the fund from a large group of small investors — sometimes investing as little as $1. We’re democratizing the investment firm.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Run by startup entrepreneurs, with veteran advisors: the best of the venture capital industry&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Instant Diversification. One investment gets you exposure to hundreds of investments.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vetted and Verified.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Like an Index Fund. Get exposure across multiple sectors, stages and geographies.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The last ICO you’ll ever need to invest in!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-it-works&quot;&gt;How it Works&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These points were extracted from various existing investor platforms, including:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://angel.co/syndicates/for-investors#funds&quot;&gt;Angelist Funds&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://angel.co/funds&quot;&gt;+&lt;/a&gt; , &lt;a href=&quot;https://republic.co/crowdsafe&quot;&gt;Republic.co&lt;/a&gt; , &lt;a href=&quot;https://eureeca.com/Static/HowItWorksInvestors.aspx&quot;&gt;Eureeca&lt;/a&gt; , &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.crowdcube.com/investing-your-money&quot;&gt;CrowdCube&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://help.crowdcube.com/hc/en-us/categories/200958429-Investing&quot;&gt;+&lt;/a&gt; , &lt;a href=&quot;https://coinlist.co&quot;&gt;CoinList&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All contributing investors are treated as a single “investor”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Legal entity which commits the capital will be setup in a tax-free, startup friendly jurisdiction (e.g. British Virgin Islands)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Investors can act as early adopters for the portfolio companies (a regular newsletter will got out with deal details to investors, so that they can&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do funds select deals? Funds are designed to give broad market exposure, either to the early-stage market generally or to a specific sector (depending on the fund in which you invest). There is a multi-stage selection process that includes, among other things, evaluating co-investors, conflicts, concentration in any one syndicate and non-arms length transactions. We may not apply the same process to every deal.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What reporting will funds do? Funds will disclose fund investments after they are finalized, and may provide qualitative updates to investors when available. Funds will not post audited financial statements. Funds will not mark valuations to market each year given the extreme difficulty of doing that in an accurate manner for early stage investments.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who can invest? Anyone over the age of 18 can invest. There are no net worth or income minimums, but U.S. law does limit how much you can invest. You do not need to be a U.S. citizen to invest.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you accept US investors? &lt;strong&gt;No.&lt;/strong&gt; The US has very strict rules on marketing to or receiving investment from US persons. Therefore, we do not allow US persons — defined as persons with single or dual US nationality, persons residing in the US, or whose primary bank account is in the US — to invest through Eureeca.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Investors can be private individuals as well as institutions. What they will all have in common is an interest in investing in high-yield potential private businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What due diligence checks are done? The due diligence check ensures that businesses applying to raise funds on Eureeca are legitimate and exist. Eureeca works with third-party compliance firms to assess if the company is incorporated, the duration of operations and that all necessary corporate and legal documents are in place. Additionally, background checks will be done on the team and founders to ensure that there is no history of fraud or other relevant criminal activity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Did you know that investing in early stage investments can generate an annual return of 27%? Bearing that in mind, how much do you think you would allocate to investing in SMEs per year?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is verified? The agency’s evaluation spans technical features of the platform in question, the business model and market niche, the team and business experience in the blockchain industry and development, strengths and weaknesses of the decentralized infrastructure, and other factors like technical background (e.g. quality of the prototype or source code), and analysis of community feedback.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ICORating conducts the research of all aspects of the project, which stand for specific cryptocurrency financial instrument. The company analyzes the investment risks of the project entering ICO, in the following areas:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;business model (its relevance, strong and weak points);&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;market niche (prospects and dynamics of the selected market niches for building business);&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;team (business experience in the traditional market segment, in blockchain industry, blockchain-development experience);&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;competition (competitive pressure level on the part of companies with similar business models of the traditional market segment and blockchain-economy);&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;technical background (availability and quality of the prototype or source code);&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;analysis of the feedback from the community;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;relevant-white-papers&quot;&gt;Relevant White Papers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://taas.fund/media/whitepaper.pdf&quot;&gt;TaaS Fund&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.daohub.org/uploads/default/original/2X/6/6589831b3add67773e4e5af745f42b73c1712c86.pdf&quot;&gt;DAO Hub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ico.encryptotel.com/assets/pdf/EncryptoTel_WP_v1.pdf&quot;&gt;EncryptoTel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/angelinvesting.html&quot;&gt;http://www.paulgraham.com/angelinvesting.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://venturehacks.com/articles/angel&quot;&gt;http://venturehacks.com/articles/angel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;notes-on-becoming-a-good-angel-investor-by-pg&quot;&gt;Notes on becoming a good angel investor (by PG)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To be a good angel investor, you have to be a good judge of potential.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you can recognize good startup founders by empathizing with them—if you both resonate at the same frequency—then you may already be a better startup picker than the median professional VC&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What makes &lt;strong&gt;a good founder&lt;/strong&gt; ? &lt;em&gt;Good founders have a healthy respect for reality. But they are relentlessly resourceful. That’s the closest I can get to the opposite of hapless. You want to fund people who are relentlessly resourceful. — PG&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bet on &lt;strong&gt;people&lt;/strong&gt; .&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The problem is not finding startups, exactly, but finding a stream of reasonably high quality ones.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you want to invest seriously, the way to get started is to bootstrap yourself off your existing connections, be a good investor in the startups you meet that way, and eventually you’ll start a chain reaction.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To be good, be decisive. There’s a hack for being decisive when you’re inexperienced: ratchet down the size of your investment till it’s an amount you wouldn’t care too much about losing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-white-paper&quot;&gt;The White Paper&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll find the final version of the paper below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/unitfund-whitepaper.pdf&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/icon-pdf.svg&quot; alt=&quot;PDF Icon&quot; /&gt; Read UnitFund Whitepaper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to think through a few things, and the white paper provided a good avenue to do so. I included things liked minimum raise amount, maximum raise, investment strategy, etc. It’s light on details, but again — I could always figure those out later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-3-draft-copy-for-the-website-&quot;&gt;Day 3: Draft copy for the Website 🌐&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to effectively write up some copy for the website, I had to think through some things. Here’s how I did that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-the-goal&quot;&gt;What is the goal?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get people to invest in the Unit Fund ICO&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-would-people-invest-in-the-ico&quot;&gt;Why would people invest in the ICO?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Opportunity to make high returns (2.5x in 7 years)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Greater trust for the fund than &lt;strong&gt;trust&lt;/strong&gt; for individual ICOs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-objections-stand-between-them-and-investing&quot;&gt;What objections stand between them and investing?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trust&lt;/strong&gt; . Why the heck should I give you my money (instead of invest it myself?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-do-you-establish-trust&quot;&gt;How do you establish trust?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Links from reputable sources&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Explain the “how” in detail — show that you have a plan.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Demonstrate knowledge in the VC industry
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;White Paper&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Blog posts&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t pretend it’s guaranteed profit. Everyone knows it is not. Be upfront about the risks and highlight them before allowing anyone to invest&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Terms and Conditions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Contact Us page: address, phone&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clear profiles/bios of the people behind the project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Showcase figures of authority&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Herd mentality — show that others have committed capital already&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;remember&quot;&gt;Remember:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.distilled.net/blog/distilled/content/how-to-kick-ass-at-copywriting-for-your-website/&quot;&gt;active voice&lt;/a&gt; , not passive voice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stay customer-focused (“you” vs. “we”)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.useronboard.com/features-vs-benefits/&quot;&gt;Benefits, not features&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;page-flow&quot;&gt;Page Flow&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Explain value proposition
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Headline&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Herd mentality — show that others have committed capital already&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Feature list&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The problem it addresses&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;How the solution works&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Plan / Roadmap&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;White Paper&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Return-prediction tool&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tackle Objections
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Put terms and conditions, with confirmation modal before investing&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Place disclaimer — no guarantees, no investors from the US&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Links from reputable sources&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Clear profiles/bios of the people behind the project&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;How to Contribute&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;FAQs&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Contact Us page: address, phone&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;design-guidelines&quot;&gt;Design Guidelines&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we’re after trust, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.creativebloq.com/web-design/12-colours-and-emotions-they-evoke-61515112&quot;&gt;Blue is the appropriate base color&lt;/a&gt; to choose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;website-draft&quot;&gt;Website Draft&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1sgBEND7Jaa2T2tD7_YouF95OoSri91HTtqrLtKwXTpI/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;a link to the draft website copy&lt;/a&gt; that I prepared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/unitfund-website-copy.pdf&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/icon-pdf.svg&quot; alt=&quot;PDF Icon&quot; /&gt; Read Website Copy draft&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-4-launch-the-website-&quot;&gt;Day 4: Launch the website 🎂&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;guidelines&quot;&gt;Guidelines&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Great design is &lt;strong&gt;crucial&lt;/strong&gt; . It’s a common thread among all of the most successful companies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have a track record that you can boast. Show off your accomplishments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find industry experts and add them to your “board” to build trust. They better be wearing suits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tasks&quot;&gt;Tasks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Check out previous successful crowdsale companies. You may need to use the Wayback Machine to see what the website looked like at the time of the respective ICOs for each one (since they’ve probably changed).
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://storj.io/tokensale&quot;&gt;Storj&lt;/a&gt; ($30M)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.basicattentiontoken.org/&quot;&gt;Brave&lt;/a&gt; ($35M in 30 seconds)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tezos.com/&quot;&gt;Tezos&lt;/a&gt; ($200M)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://contribution.district0x.io/&quot;&gt;District0x&lt;/a&gt; ($15M in 1st round)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://99bitcoins.com/bitcoin-scam-test/&quot;&gt;https://99bitcoins.com/bitcoin-scam-test/&lt;/a&gt; for guidelines of what to do/not do&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hire a copywriter to spruce it up (Skipped)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hire a front-end designer to make it look like a million bucks (Skipped, used a template)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Translate to Chinese (Skipped)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Compress images&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consolidate all scripts / styles into a single file (to reduce HTTP calls)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Include proposal update samples (Skipped)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wasn’t able to get all these done (the items marked “Skipped” were skipped). I had a day to put everything together, so time was of the essence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;design-agency&quot;&gt;Design agency&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I’d had more time, I definitely would’ve spent more time on building trust. This includes equal parts design &amp;amp; PR. I spoke to the agency that built &lt;a href=&quot;https://district0x.com/&quot;&gt;District0x gorgeous website&lt;/a&gt; and they would be able to get something similar done for about $15k (I managed to negotiate that down to $10k pre, and $10k after raising the $1m minimum).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/design-agency.png&quot; alt=&quot;$10k pre-ICO, and $10k more if we raise &amp;gt; $1m&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’d take about 2 months to put everything together. Waiting that long and fronting all that dough would be overkill for this simple experiment; so I passed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the live site &lt;a href=&quot;https://unit.fund/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-6-recruit-advisors-&quot;&gt;Day 6: Recruit advisors 👔&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideally, we’ll need advisors in the Investing + Legal space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started with people in my direct network. These folks were likely to say Yes, since I knew them all personally (thanks Hasan, Ramzy and Antonio!):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hasan Haidar [500, Partner]&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ramzy Ismail [Techstars, Director]&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Antonio Sosa [REOF Capital, MD]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were also people that I &lt;em&gt;hoped&lt;/em&gt; I’d be able to get onboard. If I closed any of these folks, there’s a much higher chance that this project would succeed (because of their reputation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This list included:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dave McClure [ex500]&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paul Graham [exYC]&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chris Sacca&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mark Cuban&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Justin Kan [exYC]&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jack Dorsey&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kevin O Leary&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jessica Alba&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Robert Herjavec&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kevin Systrom&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I put it together based on my knowledge of the investment space (and from my experience watching Shark Tank episodes). Many of the people on this list are &lt;strong&gt;ex-&lt;/strong&gt;VCs/Accelerators (since those &lt;em&gt;currently&lt;/em&gt; working at VCs/accelerators may face a conflict of interest).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before reaching out, I needed to have some sort of strategy for approaching them:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prepare a dedicated 60 second video to each one, explaining exactly what you want and what’s in it for them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prepare an image, showing all of the other folks that you plan to close, showing the recipient’s name as “Pending” (in a sea of prominent names)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; best to reach these folks, I would:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reach through mutual connections on LinkedIn (i.e. 2nd degree connections)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use &lt;a href=&quot;https://thehustle.co/the-linkedin-hack-that-made-me-120000&quot;&gt;the LinkedIn hack™&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cold-email (if all else fails)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-the-civilized-linkedin-mutual-connections-strategy&quot;&gt;1. The civilized LinkedIn mutual connections strategy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This strategy proved utterly useless. For someone else that’s well connected in the valley, it probably would’ve worked just fine. However, I only had a first/second degree connection with one person (Dave McClure) and I didn’t really know him all that well — we’d met once in Bahrain, and he probably didn’t remember.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I messaged him and - surprise, surprise - heard nothing back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All other connections were 3rd degree; fat chance that’ll work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/not-second-degree-connection.png&quot; alt=&quot;Jessica Alba is not a second-degree connection&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-the-linkedin-hack&quot;&gt;2. The LinkedIn hack&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d recommend reading through the &lt;a href=&quot;https://thehustle.co/the-linkedin-hack-that-made-me-120000&quot;&gt;original post&lt;/a&gt; for details on the mechanics of this method. My approach matched that to the dot. I would have to setup a campaign for each of the 10 people on the list, record a video and post it on a specially designed landing page. Alot of work, but hopefully it’ll pay off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will cost about $10/person x 10 people = $100 max.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The script I used for the ad was pretty simple:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/paul-ad.png&quot; alt=&quot;PG Ad&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clicking it will take you to a page similar to the one used in the hack article. It has a 60 second video - no fancy editing or anything. It also includes my contact bits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/a-message-for-paul.png&quot; alt=&quot;A message for Paul Graham&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;… and here’s a sample video that I made:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- Courtesy of embedresponsively.com //--&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;responsive-video-container&quot;&gt;

  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/9R-LDEfhzPw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are slight variations in the messages. For example, for Mr.Wonderful (Kevin o Leary), I mentioned the 2% returns first because y’know, the man likes his dollars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I found that’s very different from &lt;a href=&quot;https://thehustle.co/the-linkedin-hack-that-made-me-120000&quot;&gt;Jack’s experience&lt;/a&gt; is that the minimum size of the target audience is no longer 7. It’s about 400. That means we can’t just target a handful of folks that know each target individual — nope, we have to target their companies (and if they’ve worked in a few places, then we’ll target those too).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I think about it, an alternative may have been to create 399 fake LinkedIn accounts that you &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; won’t see the ad; its not something I tried personally though :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-7-create-a-basic-smart-contract-&quot;&gt;Day 7: Create a Basic Smart Contract 💻&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ethereum.org has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ethereum.org/crowdsale&quot;&gt;a simple tutorial on how to code one up&lt;/a&gt; . You can also create your first basic token in 15 seconds using &lt;a href=&quot;http://thetokenfactory.com/#/factory&quot;&gt;The Token Factory&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://solidity.readthedocs.io/en/latest/&quot;&gt;Solidity Docs&lt;/a&gt; are an excellent introduction to the Solidity programming language (it’s sorta like JS). Also, found a good base template &lt;a href=&quot;https://etherscan.io/address/0x725803315519de78D232265A8f1040f054e70B98#code&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I did get pretty familiar with Solidity early on, I couldn’t risk all those potential $’s by building a smart contract myself (having just completed the ‘Hello World’ Ethereum tutorial). Instead, I &lt;a href=&quot;https://upwork.com/mobile/freelances/~01af74f7d496c1817b&quot;&gt;hired Andrew Zubko from UpWork&lt;/a&gt; to get the job done on a tight deadline — he delivered, and the project cost me $1,000 in total (including deployment to the Ethereum blockchain).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll find the code for the contract &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/unitfund/contract&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-8-reach-out-to-ico-lists-&quot;&gt;Day 8: Reach out to ICO lists 🛎&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, I did not have luck on my side. All of the lists I found had some sort of priority paid option — committing the capital sin of not &lt;em&gt;paying&lt;/em&gt; these lists will result in your ICO languishing in wait for days, if not weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the list of places I reached out to (inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coindesk.com/the-ultimate-list-of-resources-for-researching-and-launching-icos/&quot;&gt;this list&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;https://www.smithandcrown.com/icos/&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;https://www.coinschedule.com/&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;https://icotracker.net/&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;https://www.ico-list.com/&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-9-publicity-&quot;&gt;Day 9: Publicity 🗞&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also reached out to various news outlets. Here, they request payment for “Press Releases”, often ~$1k each next to a free “tips” option (which I opted for):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;http://www.coindesk.com/&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;https://www.cryptocoinsnews.com/&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;https://cointelegraph.com/&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;https://bitcoinmagazine.com/&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re willing to spend ~$20k on Marketing, you could probably get listed on all of these places. I had no intention of paying that sort of money, so I passed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I drafted a Press Release and posted it on every site that had a form:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A VC fund from the future&lt;/strong&gt;
  A very different type of VC fund has just launched; it’s similar to traditional VCs in many aspects, but a crucial one: it doesn’t depend on wealthy investors.
  &lt;br /&gt;
  The UnitFund has launched the first-ever crowd-funded Venture Capital fund, democratizing access to what was once exclusively available to institutions and to the ultra-wealthy. Yazin Alirhayim, General Partner at UnitFund, explains: “Traditional VC funds, they’re very good at what they do. The top quarter of all funds see a healthy 20%+ annual return on capital invested[1]. They’ll typically double your money in under 5 years. The problem is, normal folks don’t have access to VC funds: these firms only deal with exclusive “Limited Partners” – institutions investors and ultra-high net worth individuals – for raising capital. We’re changing that.”
  &lt;br /&gt;
  In order to raise capital for their first ever fund, the UnitFund has resorted to an Intial Coin Offering (ICO), allowing early investors to purchase Unit Fund Tokens in exchange for Ethereum tokens (currently valued at about $175/ETH). They’ve capped the fund at $50M. “This is a closed-ended fund – once the Tokensale (ICO) is over, no one will be able to purchase additional tokens. The fund will be final.”, Alirhayim explained. “We may consider launching another fund sometime in the future”.
  &lt;br /&gt;
  The past few months have seen a sharp increase in the number of ICOs, and it is becoming increasingly difficult for individual investors to perform the thorough due diligence required in order to make an informed investment decision. “We employ strict industry-standard due diligence on every single investment we make – we vet every deal, and meet with the partners involved before choosing to invest”. This allows the fund to avoid “scam” ICOs that are nothing more than just an idea with a website and white paper.
  &lt;br /&gt;
  The UnitFund ICO starts tomorrow, July 26 at 9AM CET. It concludes on August 26. The first time such a fund was attempted, by Blockchain Capital in April 2017, they raised $10M in under 6 hours[2].
  &lt;br /&gt;
  More details on the UnitFund website: https://unit.fund/&lt;br /&gt;
  [1]: VC fund returns in 2016, https://www.cbinsights.com/investor-mosaic&lt;br /&gt;
  [2]: tokenhub.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I originally planned to “launch” the ICO by July 25th but I pushed it out a day when I realized that publicity wasn’t going so well. I wasn’t able to get listed on any of the ICO lists (until after the ICO). I also didn’t have any advisors on LinkedIn yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;results&quot;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You didn’t forget that this was an experiment did you? The results are the most important part of this post, so let’s dive right in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point the ICO is &lt;em&gt;almost over&lt;/em&gt; (it ends Aug 26, 9AM BST). I don’t suspect anything major is going to happen in the closing few hours, so these results are fresh as of Aug 23rd&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;linkedin-hack&quot;&gt;LinkedIn hack&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This hack &lt;strong&gt;failed&lt;/strong&gt; at the primary mission, which was to get an advisor onboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I initially ran a trial with Dave McClure, his results are here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/dave-mcclure-trial.png&quot; alt=&quot;Dave McClure results&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here are the overall results for all the LinkedIn ads I ran:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/final-ad-results.png&quot; alt=&quot;LinkedIn Ads Results&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got a few cute emails saying “wow, nice way to grab attention” from some of the people that saw it, but no contact from any of the 10 advisor prospects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there was an interesting side-effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;almost-final-score&quot;&gt;(Almost) Final Score&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people actually saw the ad, and invested. Specifically, it was 2 people that &lt;strong&gt;I do not know&lt;/strong&gt;  … who contributed a total of ~$10.5k:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/final-score.png&quot; alt=&quot;Final contribution breakdown&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s the total amount raised as of this morning, with just about one day left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; Once the ICO ends, I’ll be refunding all of the funds raised if the total remains below the $1M minimum I advertised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In conclusion, not any random person with a website and a white paper will raise millions of dollars in an ICO. This experiment failed to raise the $1M minimum, despite all the effort I put into getting it out. If I were to try again, I’d focus more on PR &amp;amp; Design — ICOs are funded in crowds, or not at all.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
.section-optional {
  background-color:#eee;
  font-size:95%;
  padding:10px;
  border-radius:5px;
}
&lt;/style&gt;</content><author><name>Yazin Alirhayim</name><email>hi@yaz.in</email></author><summary type="html">I broke the trail of the Real Estate idea to pursue what I considered a unique opportunity that pulled me into the mesmerizing world of cryptocurrency ICOs.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Real Estate Idea</title><link href="https://yazin.co/real-estate-idea/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Real Estate Idea" /><published>2017-07-02T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2017-07-02T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>https://yazin.co/real-estate-idea</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yazin.co/real-estate-idea/">&lt;p&gt;This is &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; a well-defined idea, and I still don’t know what to test — or indeed, whether there’s anything to do here. I do know that people in Bahrain buy &amp;amp; sell real-estate the same way they have in the pre-web era. The only difference is that now there’s a bunch of websites (really, not very different than catalogs, or newspaper classifieds) that advertise properties. The transaction is always initiated via a phone call, followed by a site visit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s certainly room for improvement — but before doing anything, the first step has to be about discovery. Don’t try to fix something you don’t fully understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;discovery&quot;&gt;Discovery&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many ways to understand the “real estate process”; you could ask the agents, people that want to buy a property, or the owners — those are the primary parties involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, and because I know very little about the space, I’ll start by attempting to buy a property (masquerading as a buyer). This will allow me to start at the beginning (a buyer shows interest), and then branch out to the other process directions (how did the owner list the property?) and (how does the realtor close the sale).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and I’ll do this until I feel like I’ve nailed the process (i.e. I can predict exactly what steps the next realtor will follow, to the t). That’ll probably take about 30 tries to do, maybe more. We’ll see…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-buying-process&quot;&gt;The Buying Process&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I setup viewings for 8 properties with various real-estate agents, and sourced through multiple websites. Here’s a list:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1ZXSc5S8ijY2ShoBPCKH3O6WUlaLJoOVJTm-7HsWib7A/pubhtml?gid=0&amp;amp;single=true&amp;amp;widget=true&amp;amp;headers=false&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;height:350px;border:1px solid #ccc;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having gone through all of these viewings, here’s what the buying process looks like visually, with some notes of the things I found odd:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/real-estate-buyer-process.png&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/real-estate-buyer-process.png&quot; alt=&quot;Buyer process&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-selling-process&quot;&gt;The Selling Process&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this next bit, I call up estate agents this time seeking assistance in selling my house. I then clarify the process after having called several estate agents and figured out a cohesive process map for the selling process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the list:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seller calls up the estate agent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Estate agent comes in and takes photos of the property&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Estate agent suggests the price, according to current market conditions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once price is decided, the agent posts the property on the various channels (website, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the buyer decides on purchasing the property, a price negotiation is conducted&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the buyer decided to proceed, they both meet at the notary and sign over the title deed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/real-estate-seller-process.png&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/real-estate-seller-process.png&quot; alt=&quot;Seller process&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;deciding-on-a-problem&quot;&gt;Deciding on a problem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, I have several candidates for problems to sovle — all of them from notes I picked up during the buying process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve listed what seem to be the most promising candidates here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The issue of handling keys. In the instances I witnessed, the agents either had to drive out of their way to get the keys from someplace, or were just unable to provide the keys at all because they didn’t have them handy. I already have several ideas for solutions, but let’s not get ahead of ourselves.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Agents ask for the price of the property in order to identify which one you’re talking about. Do they not have an app for this? How do they track their properties? Worth exploring… Also tied to two other issues:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Offered homes for viewing that were not listed on the site&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The issue where the agent didn’t know the status of the home because the owner was non-responsive.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, I need to talk to some real estate agents to see if this is something that might actually fly — since they would be the customer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I pulled up LinkedIn, and started searching for 1st and 2nd degree connections with people in the real-estate industry, specifically agents and owners of agencies. I also decided to put together a draft to ask &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bahrainpropertyworld.com/bahrain-property-and-real-estate-agents/&quot;&gt;a whole list of real-estate agents&lt;/a&gt; that I had no relation with. Mind you, this was a list of agencies, not agents — so I’d still have to do a bunch of digging to find the contact details for specific agents. Still, totally doable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, I need a script. Here’s what I used:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey [Name]? ⏸  My name’s Yazin, I’m a business student working on a project to help real-estate agents. Could you help answer some questions for me? It’ll only be a few minutes ⏸  Great. Let’s say I was looking to buy a house. How would you look up the details of the property? Do you have some sort of system you use, or is it something more basic? ⏸  Ok, and how does that work if you’re outside the office? ⏸  Great, now my last set of questions are going to be about the keys to the houses on sale. Do the owners usually keep the keys or do you hold on to them? ⏸  Where do you usually keep them? ⏸  What happens if another real-estate agent has a client that wants to see the property? ⏸&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, I put together the list of agents:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1ZljRuyjHNza7LeJUMpNwgVITKTvT4nyVzNXZ0aKV2FQ/pubhtml?gid=0&amp;amp;single=true&amp;amp;widget=true&amp;amp;headers=false&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; height:400px;border:1px solid #ccc;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;… and started talking!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was originally planning on speaking to all 55 agents in the list, but I found that the answers were pretty much all the same after #8, so I didn’t see a reason to continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was able to learn that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keys problem&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In most cases, the property keys are kept with the property owners. In the remaining ~20% of cases, they are either kept with property managers, security guard/watchmen or are handed over to the real estate agent (in case of an exclusive arrangement between owner and agent).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If another agent refers a client, then they split the commission (often down the middle). However, there’s a database of properties for sale/on rent that’s used by many real estates which lists the contact details of the owners. This means that in some cases, the real estate agent with the client can cut out the listing agent and close the deal with the owner directly. It’s unclear how big of an issue this is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From what I’ve learned, the key problem seems more worthwhile to pursue but it’s obviously &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; going to be a pure software solution. Some hardware would be needed to grant/revoke access to the property, even if it’s just &lt;a href=&quot;https://toor.today&quot;&gt;a lockbox&lt;/a&gt; (that project appears to be dead btw, after the owner raised ~$500k from KickStarter &amp;amp; Shark tank).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Systems problem&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Every agent uses some sort of system (even if that’s just basic Excel for small agencies), but none of them seemed to be aware that there was an issue — nor did they complain about it much.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are 12.5 million results on Google for “real estate CRM”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also did come along another problem that I hadn’t thought about before:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Competition problem&lt;/strong&gt;:
One thing I picked up from the conversations is that real estate agents have a dim view of &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; real estate agents — and there’s always a worry that they are going to steal from each other. One particular example is how they don’t share all of the information pertaining to a property on their website, since that would mean other real estate agents might be able to see it too (and copy it). Of course, the more real estate agents know about a property, the more likely a buyer will end up seeing it, and the more likely it’ll get sold. However, real estate agents are not incentivized to work together, but work &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; each other in order to make a (commission-based) living. It is strange that things like address and nearby points of interest are hidden to prevent this “theft” from taking place. This means that the customer can’t know the exact location of the property without first contacting the estate agent. Additionally, it means that if he/she wanted to view mutliple properties in the same location — they’d need to coordinate with multiple agents and hope that they can line them all up in the same window. This is a sucky situation for all the parties involved: propspective buyer, agent and the seller. The only parties you really need in order to execute a buy/sell agreement is the buyer and the seller — the agent’s role should be to add value as a middleman, not get in the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So to take a step back, let’s consider the value proposition of using an agent in the first place:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They can do viewings for the owner, so the owner doesn’t have to show up to the property every time a prospective buyer comes by.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They (supposedly) help find buyers. I say supposedly, since many people today seem to find properties (either via &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bahrainpropertyworld.com/&quot;&gt;one&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.propertyfinder.bh/&quot;&gt;of&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bestbahrainproperties.com/en/&quot;&gt;the&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://century21.bh/&quot;&gt;many&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://bahrain.youramlak.com/&quot;&gt;websites&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bahrainpropertylocators.com/&quot;&gt;existence&lt;/a&gt;, or by just passing by a property with a sign).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the downsides…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They take a fee from both the seller (~2%) and the buyer (1%)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They don’t always have the best interest of the buyer OR the seller at heart. Since they get paid a % of the sale price, their goal is to maxmimize that price. That’s obviously bad for buyers, but it’s also bad for the seller if they’re looking to sell on some sort of timeline (and not wait forever).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Their scattered nature means that you often have to talk to mulitple agents to see a group of properties in the same location (no one agent has access to all of the properties; they might not even be aware of all of them in the first place).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first impression is: wow, that’s nuts. I mean, there’s got to be more to what estate agents do than just (literally) unlocking doors and putting up signs! Maybe there’s some psychological element I’m overlooking — a sense of security knowing that you’re dealing with someone who’s sold tens of houses before and know’s what they’re doing. Yeah, may be. Still, it seems really overpriced for what you’re getting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first impression is: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fastcompany.com/3001334/want-disrupt-industry-try-actually-working-it-first&quot;&gt;before I cross them off as useless, it’s a good idea to get in their shoes&lt;/a&gt; for a while… see what it feels like to actually get people to buy/rent a property, and then figure out whether they do indeed add value or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; I’m working on a side-project so this’ll be on hold for a few days while I see what transpires with the other idea. Expect an update on Wed, 19th July.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update (28/July)&lt;/strong&gt;: Ok, so the other project took longer than I expected, and is already underway. It hasn’t concluded yet (it’ll take about a month from today), but it won’t take up as much time from me as it did these past 2 weeks. I’ll be continuing with this project from the 4th of August, once I’m back from a quick trip.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Yazin Alirhayim</name><email>hi@yaz.in</email></author><summary type="html">This isn't a particular idea, but a possibility. I've had very little experience with real estate, but I'm sure there's a way to make it at least 10x better, either for the buyer or for the agents themselves.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Validator</title><link href="https://yazin.co/the-validator/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Validator" /><published>2017-06-30T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2017-06-30T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>https://yazin.co/the-validator</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yazin.co/the-validator/">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;/the-gforms-idea/&quot;&gt;GForms’s Landing page&lt;/a&gt; took me about 10 days to build, launch and validate — most of it spent on the damn front-end making sure everything looked OK on mobile and desktop. Once I ran the experiment, within 24 hours I knew it was not going to fly. The question is, could I have finished it sooner?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You bet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This idea is to make a simple tool that helps you validate an idea quickly. No more slogging through creating a landing page, hooking up Intercom, etc. A/B testing messaging and running experiments. This tool has all the best practices built-in, and makes the process smooth as silk. $99/month, and you’ll still save so much time and money!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the idea anyway. Let’s see if it picks up any steam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;approach-to-validation&quot;&gt;Approach to Validation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Step one, as ever, is to validate your riskiest assumption. Let’s break out the busines model canvas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;business-model-canvas&quot;&gt;Business Model Canvas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/business-model-canvas-validate.png&quot; alt=&quot;Business Model Canvas&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;landing-page&quot;&gt;Landing Page&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, with that out of the way it’s clear that I’m going to need a landing page to test things out. I decided to build it using a landing page builder (as opposed to hand-coding it, which took forever &lt;a href=&quot;/the-gforms-idea/&quot;&gt;last time&lt;/a&gt;). I settled on &lt;a href=&quot;http://instapage.com&quot;&gt;InstaPage&lt;/a&gt;, and was able to get familiar with it pretty quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process went like so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open up Google Docs and type up the copy for the page.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sketch the layout on paper&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Implement it in InstaPage (I also used Mailchimp for collecting emails)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Buy a domain (I used &lt;a href=&quot;http://validate.tech&quot;&gt;validate.tech&lt;/a&gt; for this experiment)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was all super-quick, and took just a few hours to put together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the end result (Yeah, I know … super-long, and text-heavy):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/landing-page-validate.png&quot; alt=&quot;Landing Page - Validate&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll notice a Login link there (that’s fake, and leads to an empty page with a fake login screen that does nothing) and an address (also fake).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;launching-the-experiment&quot;&gt;Launching the experiment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, we need to make sure we’ve got clear goals ahead of the experiment. Mine was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Target visitor count: 1,000 visits&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Target conversion rate to payer: 1% (so, 10 * $49/mo. minimum = $490/mo.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t have a payment flow setup, it would just ask for your email and then say “Thanks!” before you had a chance to pay — but it does show intent to pay, which is what I care about right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;hackernews--producthunt&quot;&gt;HackerNews &amp;amp; ProductHunt&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hackernews link &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=14654999&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ProductHunt link &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.producthunt.com/posts/validate&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time, the results were pretty dismal from both channels … the grand total was:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/analytics-validate-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Analytics&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;51 visitors; 0 conversions. Damn, that’s horrible. The Google Forms idea raked in 1,000 visits per channel (2k visitors total) so I was expecting something similar. However, it seems that was naive — many people thought that the Google Forms idea was an &lt;em&gt;actual Google product&lt;/em&gt;, and hence the interest. This idea didn’t have that going for it, so no free ride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hmm. I need to figure out a way to get more traffic so that the results are at least statistically significant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;reddit--everything-else&quot;&gt;Reddit &amp;amp; everything else&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a bid to get more visits, I made sure to submit it everywhere where my target audience might hang out. This included:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/programming/comments/6khslc/test_your_startup_idea_in_under_24_hours/&quot;&gt;r/programming&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://softwareengineering.stackexchange.com/questions/351961/how-can-i-effectively-test-a-product-idea-before-building-it&quot;&gt;Software Engineering @ StackExchange&lt;/a&gt; — yes, I posted a question linking to my site so folks would click it. Shoot me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This won’t get me to 1,000 visits. Instead of spending money to get more visits (via ads), I decided to maximize the data I get per visit. I added &lt;a href=&quot;http://crazyegg.com&quot;&gt;CrazyEgg&lt;/a&gt; for both heatmaps (which they are well known for), as well as a new feature they’d launched called Recordings (which record everything the user does on your site). Here’s what that looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/crazyegg-recordings-validate.png&quot; alt=&quot;Recordings&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Excellent. I waited till the next day for the results to come in:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/analytics-validate-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Google Analytics - Take 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, so that’s 100 more visits since yesterday. When digging through the CrazyEgg logs, I noticed something interesting:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/analytics-try-clicks.png&quot; alt=&quot;Clicks on Try Validate&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looks like 5% of visitors were interested in “Try Validate”, a button I’d added at the bottom of the page that simply scrolls up to the pricing section. Hmm, maybe a free trial would’ve converted better than … well, nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then checked the leads, and was surprised to see one lead:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/leads-validate-one.png&quot; alt=&quot;Leads&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hmm, using a Gmail address for an enterprise plan does not seem promising — but hey, I sent an email out to Joe anyway to see why he signed up for a demo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technically, that makes for a conversion rate of 1 / 150 = ~0.7% vs the goal of 1% — but again, this depends on how this Joe lead turns out. I’m (hopelessly?) optimistic it’ll pan out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;results&quot;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Update: By the next day, I had 300+ visitors total (most of it from Reddit/programming). No improvement in leads though — still just the 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/analytics-validate-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Analytics - Final&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The numbers speak for themselves — this experiment failed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Yazin Alirhayim</name><email>hi@yaz.in</email></author><summary type="html">I found it very time consuming to test out the last 2 ideas, and I'm wondering if there's a quicker way to do that specifically for testing out product ideas. That's what I'll be testing with this experiment.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Gforms Idea</title><link href="https://yazin.co/the-gforms-idea/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Gforms Idea" /><published>2017-06-29T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2017-06-29T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>https://yazin.co/the-gforms-idea</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yazin.co/the-gforms-idea/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: I actually ran this experiment about 2 weeks before I posted this, but wanted to document everything here — hence this post&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright, let’s hit another idea and see what we can learn. This one goes like so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A forms app that works on mobile and is offline. Maybe include an Android widget so you can tap, tap, done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A subscription service, that offers the ability to submit Google Forms offline. I use GForms alot, and I’m betting there’s others out there that do too (how many there are remains a question that needs answering).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having the ability to submit forms offline means people that use it for expense tracking can do so painlessly, and from anywhere — those that use it for any other sort of mobile tracking can do the same. It would be very useful to a small set of people that (a) use Google Forms frequently and (b) are on the move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frankly, I have no idea how the heck people could possibly use this (and indeed, if anyone would want to use this thing) — hence, the experiment. All I know is that there are many, many users of Google products and if even a small subset of those will find this beneficial, then there’s plenty of room to make a business here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;approach-to-validation&quot;&gt;Approach to Validation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;landing-page&quot;&gt;Landing Page&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time I didn’t use the Business Model Canvas like last time, since I don’t know what the use-case (and hence, the market) is for this product. Instead, I’ll use a landing page showing this feature — and launch it on HackerNews / ProductHunt. That way, I’ll guage the response and create a specific product based on the feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, what I’ll do is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create a simple landing page showing the main feature&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Launch it on HackerNews / ProductHunt&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reach out to signups and ask them why they signed up&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create a specific product based on feedback&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hand-coded the landing page, though that turned out to be a very time-consuming process (especially having to make sure everything looked well on desktop and mobile). It would’ve made more sense to simple use &lt;a href=&quot;http://unbounce.com&quot;&gt;one&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://instapage.com&quot;&gt;of&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://optimizely.com&quot;&gt;the&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://wix.com&quot;&gt;many&lt;/a&gt; landing page tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what I came up with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/landing-page-gforms.png&quot; alt=&quot;Landing Page&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And once you hit the “Try it” button, you get a simple modal:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/modal-gforms.png&quot; alt=&quot;Modal&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you press the “How it Works”, it cycles through a series of device screenshots that demonstrate the apps functionality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/landing-page-gforms-screens.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screens&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The emails are submitted to a Google Firebase database so the whole page is static. I then booked the domain &lt;a href=&quot;http://formsapp.me&quot;&gt;formsapp.me&lt;/a&gt; and put it up (using &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/dokku/dokku&quot;&gt;Dokku&lt;/a&gt;, a roll-your-own Heroku solution).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;launching-the-experiment&quot;&gt;Launching the experiment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before launching, I had to set a clear goal for what the target response rate would be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The figures I put down were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Target visitor count: 1,000 visits&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Target conversion rate to subscriber: 20% (since it’s free)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that out of the way, it was time to launch the landing page. I chose HackerNews and ProductHunt as my channels of choice — since that’s where the most likely target customer base lies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;hackernews&quot;&gt;HackerNews&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was simple enough:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/landing-page-gforms-hackernews.png&quot; alt=&quot;Hacker News submission&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=14580353&quot;&gt;submitted it&lt;/a&gt; on Sunday afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;producthunt&quot;&gt;ProductHunt&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a bit more involved. I had to submit the screenshots of the (make-believe) mobile app along with an icon. I noticed that GIF images were more likely to grab attention, so I made one quickly to go along with the page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find the submission &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.producthunt.com/posts/formsapp&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/landing-page-gforms-producthunt.png&quot; alt=&quot;ProductHunt submission&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;results&quot;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I waited for 24 hours, and then checked Google Analytics for results:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/gforms-analytics-result.png&quot; alt=&quot;Google Analytics&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not bad. I managed to score 2,000 visits in total after just 1 day. I also checked the database, but that was much less encouraging: I only managed to get 14 emails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That meant a dismal conversion rate of 14 / 2000 = 0.7% (a far cry from the 20% rate I’d set). And I wasn’t even asking for any money..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not encouraging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, I decided I’d reach out to the 14 emails and ask them for their feedback. I sent out to the following email to the folks that signed up:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/gforms-email.png&quot; alt=&quot;Email&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I managed to get several responses from the people I reached out, a total of 5 of the 14 responded — and all of them said that they were B (just curious).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;verdict&quot;&gt;Verdict&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The numbers have spoken — this idea is officially dead.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Yazin Alirhayim</name><email>hi@yaz.in</email></author><summary type="html">I use Google Forms alot, primarily to track my finances (and also with calorie counting). One quirk is that they don't have an offline solution &amp;mdash; I'm wondering if there are other people out there that find that valuable enough to pay for.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Goals Idea</title><link href="https://yazin.co/the-goals-idea/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Goals Idea" /><published>2017-06-27T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2017-06-27T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>https://yazin.co/the-goals-idea</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yazin.co/the-goals-idea/">&lt;p&gt;The first idea I’ll be testing is one that I’ve had for a while. The description I had from &lt;a href=&quot;/ideas/&quot;&gt;the Ideas list&lt;/a&gt; is this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The way that large companies propagate high-level goals down from leadership to employees across the company is broken. It ends up becoming a formality, done over Powerpoint slides twice a year (beginning and end, during performance reviews). This is a lost opportunity, one where goals could serve as the glue that ties employees daily work towards a greater company objective. Coupled with transparency, employees can see exactly how they impact the greater goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;approach-to-validation&quot;&gt;Approach to Validation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;business-model-canvas&quot;&gt;Business Model Canvas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since this is the first idea I’ll be validating, I’d like to try out the most obvious method — the infamous Business Model Canvas. So I fill it in like so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/business-model-canvas-goals-idea.png&quot; alt=&quot;Business Model Canvas&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent about 30 minutes filling that in (I used &lt;a href=&quot;http://leanstack.com/&quot;&gt;LeanStack&lt;/a&gt; to get it done). Ok, the idea was pretty vague when I started — and now it does seem &lt;em&gt;abit&lt;/em&gt; more concrete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;riskiest-assumption&quot;&gt;Riskiest Assumption&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step would be to “validate my riskiest assumption”. I’ll list down all of the assumptions I have going on (aside from the canvas, in it’s entirety):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Large companies still share goals via Powerpoint slides twice a year&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Large companies &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; transparency in their goals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Employees are incentivized to use the tool and can benefit from it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The challenge I’m sensing in this goal is a greater one — one that relates to product adoption. How the heck am I going to convince a large corporation (one with 1k+ employees) to pay for a tool that doesn’t yet exist — and for a problem that they may not even be aware they have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tall order indeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that’s our concern then: &lt;strong&gt;do customers know they have a problem?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I have no intention of building the product without paying customers lined up, I’m necessarily going to have to start with smaller companies (&amp;lt;100 employees).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;validate-it&quot;&gt;Validate It&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to test out this assumption, I decided to run some interviews. For this, I primarily relied on &lt;a href=&quot;http://customerdevlabs.com/2013/11/05/how-i-interview-customers/&quot;&gt;Justin Wilcox’s proven interviewing tips&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My process was simple:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reach out to small businesses (with between 10 - 100 employees)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interview the Founder/CEO&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Analyze results&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To reach out to the founders, I used &lt;a href=&quot;http://mattermark.com&quot;&gt;MatterMark’s dashboard search&lt;/a&gt;. It’s awesome because it lets you search companies by number of employees. I then wrote emails out to the Founder/CEO’s of the first 50 companies on the list. The email address is often firstname@company.domain&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what one of those emails looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/email-strategy-interview.png&quot; alt=&quot;Email&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expected to hear back from half of the folks — so about 25 (especially since I offered to compensate them for their time, something I learned from &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/74338272&quot;&gt;Jason Cohen&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also drafted a few questions that I’d ask in the interview. Here are some of them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who defines the strategy for the company?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How is it communicated with the employees?
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What tools do you use?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;How often is the strategy revisited with the employees to align tasks with larger goals?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was more to guide the discussion — I expected to be asking alot if “why” questions too, to understand what was going on underneath the surface. I did not plan to do &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; selling on this call — that would happen later, once we’ve validated that customers are aware of this problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;results&quot;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had 0 positive responses within 3 days of sending the email out. 5 people replied to kindly say no, they were not interested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s reasonable to assume that if they really did have a hard time communicating the company strategy throughout the organization, they would’ve replied (barring some sort of email deliverability issue, which I knew was not the case).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;revisiting-the-business-model-canvas&quot;&gt;Revisiting the Business Model Canvas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went back to my business model canvas, and thought about my definition of early adopter. It was, of course, super-general. Maybe there was some way to narrow it down to a smaller group that face a more severe variant of this problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ideal group of early adopters:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;have the problem you defined&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;know they have the problem&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;are paying to “solve it” (albeit, inadequately)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The folks I’m reaching out to meet none of these criteria (which may be why the acceptance rate is so dismal). Seems like I’ll need to be much more specific about what folks I’m looking for here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s define the problem more:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I want to help &lt;strong&gt;entrepreneurs&lt;/strong&gt; solve their &lt;strong&gt;strategy communication&lt;/strong&gt; problem&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t seem to be able to &lt;strong&gt;define&lt;/strong&gt; the problem, and therefore I can’t even begin to fix it. I’ve tried searching for externally observable behaviors that suggest that this problem exists (e.g. “i don’t know &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; to work on! too many tasks on &lt;strong&gt;__&lt;/strong&gt;”) on Twitter but couldn’t find anything. I also tried searching for blog posts, etc. and also came up short. So while this problem may seem like it might exist somewhere, I have no conceivable way of detecting (let alone reaching) those that have it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence, there’s nothing more to do here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;verdict&quot;&gt;Verdict&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Experiment failed, because I was unable to find people that face the purported problem this idea solves.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Yazin Alirhayim</name><email>hi@yaz.in</email></author><summary type="html">This is the first idea I'm testing. The idea is one I've had for a while, since my time at GE. I'd like to see if I can get this hashed out and tested, quickly.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Finding An Idea</title><link href="https://yazin.co/finding-an-idea/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Finding An Idea" /><published>2017-06-25T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2017-06-25T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>https://yazin.co/finding-an-idea</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yazin.co/finding-an-idea/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;getting-an-idea&quot;&gt;Getting an idea&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding something to work on can be daunting. When you choose to work on something, you’re also choosing &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to work on countless other things. The FOMO beast in me wreaks havoc at the mere mention of such a quandary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what do I do? How can I take a decision — the right decision — at a time when there are so many things going on in so many different fields. For a split second, I want to dive into all of them: Biotechnology, Nutrition, Self-driving cars, Machine Learning, Nanotechnology, Bitcoin, Drones and so many more! There’s so much to learn, and so &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt; time! (It doesn’t help that I’m addicted to learning, and enjoy it immensely — even for it’s own sake).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I come back to my senses, I realize that’s why it’s crucial to have a framework for making decisions: a plan, based on a &lt;em&gt;key insight&lt;/em&gt; . Similar to how Jeff Bezos, all those years ago, decided that books would be a great foundation for starting an eCommerce company, since there are way too many titles to keep under one roof: since variety is key, this lead to the ultimate defensible business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s so simple — but &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; in retrospect. The idea now is to come up with such insights looking forward, and building a defensible business upon a key insight — essentially, to pull a “Jeff Bezos”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;approach&quot;&gt;Approach&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The high-level approach is a simple one:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get as many ideas as possible. The more, the merrier.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mercilessly kill the bad ideas. Oh, and make sure you do it quickly and painlessly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of this post will include a framework I devised for brainstorming ideas based on my unique experiences and interests. The approach is one that can be generalized to your case, with a little bit of self-awareness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;getting-alot-of-ideas&quot;&gt;Getting alot of ideas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-obvious-way-brainstorming&quot;&gt;The obvious way (Brainstorming)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most obvious way to generate alot of ideas is to just do a brain-dump. Grab a bunch of sticky notes, a marker and write out as many ideas as you can in 5 minutes. The limitation with this approach though is that the results are inconsistent — and the ideas you get are largely influenced by whatever it is your brain was busy thinking about &lt;em&gt;at that specific time&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-methodical-way&quot;&gt;The methodical way&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the limitations of the first method, I decided to also use a more methodical approach for completeness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the post describes this methodical approach in detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Considerations for finding a business idea:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ride a Technological Wave&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My Background &amp;amp; Expertise&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consider Regional Challenges&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;-ride-a-technological-wave&quot;&gt;① Ride a Technological Wave&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some technologies today that are going to fundamentally change how existing businesses operate. This is the perfect time to pick those up, understand the implications that they might have on incumbents and act accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be thorough about this would require exhaustive study of all technological changes, and a detailed dive into each one to understand how it might affect existing markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;VCs are perfectly positioned to write about these things, since they are on the receiving end of many startup proposals (many of which are built on top of existing technological waves).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can benefit from their insight here to help us get from a broad matrix of markets and technologies to a more narrowly focused list that I can then select from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ben Evans (click to expand)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Machine Learning&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Electric &amp;amp; Autonomous cars&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Virtual &amp;amp; Mixed reality&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;E-commerce vs Physical stores&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.foundrygroup.com/themes/&quot;&gt;Brad Feld&lt;/a&gt; ( &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.feld.com/archives/2012/12/ignore-trends-and-predictions.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; , and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.foundrygroup.com/blog/2008/03/what-is-thematic-investing/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; )&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://a16z.com/2015/01/22/16-things/&quot;&gt;a16z&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Popular trends:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://a16z.com/2015/01/22/sensorification-of-the-enterprise/&quot;&gt;Sensorification of the Enterprise&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://a16z.com/2015/01/22/machine-learning-big-data/&quot;&gt;Machine Learning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://a16z.com/2015/01/22/the-full-stack-startup/&quot;&gt;Full stack Startup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://a16z.com/2015/01/22/containers/&quot;&gt;Containers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://a16z.com/2015/01/22/security/&quot;&gt;Security&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://a16z.com/2015/01/22/online-marketplaces/&quot;&gt;Marketplaces&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://a16z.com/2015/01/22/bitcoin-and-blockchain/&quot;&gt;Bitcoin &amp;amp; Blockchain&lt;/a&gt; ( &lt;a href=&quot;http://a16z.com/2014/01/21/why-bitcoin-matters-2/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; too)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://a16z.com/2015/01/22/cloud-client-computing/&quot;&gt;Cloud-client computing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://a16z.com/2015/01/22/digital-health/&quot;&gt;Digital Health&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://a16z.com/2015/01/22/online-video/&quot;&gt;Online video &amp;amp; advertising&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://a16z.com/2015/01/22/crowdfunding/&quot;&gt;Crowdfunding&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://a16z.com/2015/01/22/insurance/&quot;&gt;Insurance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://a16z.com/2015/01/22/internet-of-things/&quot;&gt;Internet of Things&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://a16z.com/2015/01/22/devops/&quot;&gt;DevOps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ycombinator.com/rfs/&quot;&gt;YC RFS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Energy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A.I.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Robotics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Biotech&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Healthcare&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pharmaceuticals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Education&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Human Augmentation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;VR and AR&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Transportation &amp;amp; Housing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One Million Jobs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Programming Tools&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hollywood 2.0&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Diversity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enterprise Software&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Financial Services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Computer Security&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Global Health Non profits&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Underserved Communities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Food and Farming&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mass Media&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improving Democracy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Future of Work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;News&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Water&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;-my-background--expertise&quot;&gt;② My Background &amp;amp; Expertise&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ideal startup will build on my strengths — both industry-specific and otherwise. While it’s certainly possible to excel in a field I have no experience in (I knew nothing about credit cards before White), it’s preferable to choose one that I know well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take stock of what areas I’m good at, and have experience in:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gemeasurement.com/condition-monitoring-and-protection&quot;&gt;Condition Monitoring &amp;amp; Vibration Monitoring&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lean Six Sigma&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SAP&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Print Industry (print.bh)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fine Art Canvas (canvas.bh)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Online Payments &amp;amp; Credit Cards (whitepayments.com)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Drones (Teleport)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These span multiple industries (⚡️ Energy, 🖨 Print, 💲 Payments) and disciplines (Engineering, Quality, Founder, Product).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My Strengths:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I learn &lt;em&gt;quickly&lt;/em&gt; . I savor the acceleration in learning (going from 0% knowledge about something→80% of it)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I have an innate ability to simplify complicated things.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I know how to plan, and plan well.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open to feedback, in all it’s forms. No matter how harsh.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’m &lt;em&gt;complexities&lt;/em&gt; worst enemy. I can take super complicated things, and break them down into bite-size, easy-to-understand chunks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My Weaknesses:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I hate slogging through the remaining 20% (from 80→100%).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I can make the high-level plan, and execute the big juicy parts of it — but won’t comb through the minutiae.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;-consider-regional-challenges&quot;&gt;③ Consider Regional Challenges&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all of this talk about technological change will influence the world equally. The Middle East is still behind the US in some fundamental aspects of doing business e.g. logistics, payments and (perhaps as a result) eCommerce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;All problems must be verified&lt;/em&gt; (we assume they are true, but they might not be)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;High mobile penetration, low availability of &lt;em&gt;physical&lt;/em&gt; online services (Uber/Careem are notable exceptions). No clear market leader equivalent of eBay, Shyp, TaskRabbit, Stripe (or underlying ACH/SEPA for that matter). 
Recent entrants: Instashop (=Instacart).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Key learning from my time in eCommerce: mobile is exploding, and people will buy online where there’s an incentive to do so.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Financial inclusion: reaching the X-million people that don’t have bank accounts or credit cards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lack of credit history for individuals and companies in the region&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lack of delivery infrastructure to non-core cities in Saudi Arabia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Industry-specific challenges&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;⚡️ Energy
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The UAE has the largest per capita carbon footprint in the world [ &lt;a href=&quot;https://home.kpmg.com/ae/en/home/insights/2016/09/goinggreen-renewableopportunitiesintheuae.html&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt; , 2016]&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Dependence on oil [ &lt;a href=&quot;http://oilprice.com/Energy/Crude-Oil/Middle-East-Oil-Addiction-Could-Spell-Disaster.html&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt; , 2015]&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Cost of renewables without subsidies near parity with fossil fuel in the UAE [ &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ethz.ch/content/dam/ethz/special-interest/mavt/energy-science-center-dam/events/the-global-energy-challenge/steven-hartman-ge-presentation.pdf&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt; , Pg8, 2017]&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;🖨 Print
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Print industry in Middle East is … booming? [ &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.smitherspira.com/news/2017/march/middle-east-presents-new-boom-market-for-print&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt; , 2017]. They still have to contend with lower and lower prices though.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;💲 Payments
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Still no way for individuals to process online payments, without having to get a Trade License (for AED10k+). Stripe users &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.stripe.com/questions/sole-proprietor-without-federal-ein&quot;&gt;can&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;No Payouts infrastructure available for doing cheap/free bank transfers across the UAE (nevermind the region)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Transfers across the region go through SWIFT, and cost ~AED50/transfer (plus currency exchange fees)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;putting-it-all-together&quot;&gt;Putting it all together&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make this all work, I’ll start by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Matching technologies up with my strengths/background&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tying the resulting list with the list of the region’s problems to check suitability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find a key insight for each remaining idea _ (where possible)_&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I also want to leave room for random ideas that might not necessarily have surfaced through any of the previous steps. It’s totally fine to not overthink them, as long as we develop a quick way to test these ideas for viability.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Yazin Alirhayim</name><email>hi@yaz.in</email></author><summary type="html">The first step is finding an idea, one of the most intimidating parts of this whole process. In this post, I describe how I go about tackling this</summary></entry></feed>